Zhian N. Kamvar, PhD

Dept. of Infectious Disease Epidemiology
Imperial College London W2 1NY, UK
H +44 7444 840264
B zkamvar@gmail.com
https://zkamvar.netlify.com

Twitter: @zkamvar

I am a **highly-motivated software engineer** of several published packages for both population genetics/genomics and epidemiology in the R programming language. As a domain expert in computational biology, software engineer, and a science communicator, I have both the specialist and generalist skillsets needed for efficient communication and collaboration between team members with diverse technical backgrounds.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Curriculum: 5 years experience in collaborative open source lesson development targeted towards

interdisciplinary and diverse audiences

Developed lessons for **9 workshops** that reached >300 people in international conferences

Collaboratively developed **5 tutorial websites** in **RMarkdown and blogdown** to host discoverable lessons for non-technical audiences

Trained in evidence-based undergraduate STEM teaching (CIRTL)

Technology: Highly experienced (8 years) in collaborative development with Git and GitHub; managing

teams and code review

Expert R developer of several widely used R packages (poppr, aweek, incidence) (8 years)

Maintained reproducible research compendium in Docker (2 years) under continuous

integration (Kamvar et al. 2017)

Experienced in creating unique **Python** 3 modules for simulation analysis pipeline (**3 years**)

Highly experienced with continuous integration (Travis (6 years), Appveyor, and CircleCI)

for automated testing on multiple platforms

Communication: Highly experienced in quickly troubleshooting and resolving $>\!200$ forum questions in

community forums for the poppr and adegenet packages (\sim 1 day turnaround)

Co-founder and host (5 years) of award-winning science communication radio program,

Inspriration Dissemination (http://blogs.oregonstate.edu/inspiration/)

Published 19 peer-reviewed publications including 7 first-author publications

LEADERSHIP

2018–2019 **Lead Developer**, *R4Epis Project*, Médecins Sans Frontières (Doctors Without Borders).

Remote collaboration with diverse team of developers and field epidemiologists to create a well-tested series of templates and tutorials for automated outbreak and survey data analysis.

2018–Present Coordinator of Software Development, R Epidemics Consortium (RECON).

Worked with software developers, mathematical modellers, and field epidemiologists to design quality standards for software development, validation testing, and analysis of epidemiological data.

SELECTED WORKSHOPS/PRIMERS

2014-2015 https://grunwaldlab.github.io/Population_Genetics_in_R.

3-hour workshop on R for population genetic analysis using the poppr package.

2016-Present https://popgen.nescent.org.

Peer-reviewed community-submitted tutorials for population genetic analysis in R

2017 https://everhartlab.github.io/IntroR.

Introduction to R for plant pathologists including data import, reshaping, and graphics

2018-Present https://reconlearn.org/post/stegen.

Introduction to R for epidemiologists including data cleaning, graphics, and descriptive analysis

SELECTED PROJECTS (ON GITHUB)

R package: **grunwaldlab/poppr** (maintainer) analysis of populations with mixed reproductive modes

Analysis: everhartlab/sclerotinia-366 fully automated and reproducible analysis in Docker

EMPLOYMENT

2018-Present Research Softare Engineer, Imperial College London.

Developed well-tested R packages for field epidemiology and modelling

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 1 first-author)

2017–2018 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, *University of Nebraska-Lincoln*.

Population genetics of the white mold pathogen Scleortinia sclerotiorum

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 2 first-author)

2012–2016 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *Oregon State University*, (Dissertation Research).

Development and application of tools for genetic analysis of clonal populations

(9 peer-reviewed publications, 4 first-author)

QUALIFICATIONS

2016 **Ph.D. Botany and Plant Pathology**, *Oregon State University (OSU)*, Corvallis, OR, USA. Dissertation: Development and Application of Tools for Analysis of Clonal Populations

2007 **B.S. Biology**, *Truman State University (TSU)*, Kirksville, MO, USA.

SELECTED PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Kamvar ZN, López-Uribe MM, Coughlan S, Grünwald NJ, Lapp H, Manel S (2016). Developing educational resources for population genetics in R: an open and collaborative approach. *Molecular Ecology Resources*.
 17:1 120-128 doi: 10.1111/1755-0998.12558

Kamvar ZN, Amaradasa BS, Jhala R, McCoy S, Steadman JR, Everhart SE (2017). Population structure
and phenotypic variation of Sclerotinia sclerotiorum from dry bean (Phaseolus vulgaris) in the United States.

PeerJ **5**:e4152 doi: 10.7717/peerj.4152

data/analysis: https://github.com/everhartlab/sclerotinia-366

doi: 10.17605/OSF.IO/EJB5Y

Personal References

Richard G. FitzJohn (colleague)

Research Software Engineer
Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology
Imperial College London
r.fitzjohn@imperial.ac.uk

Sydney E. Everhart (former postdoc advisor)

Assistant Professor
Department of Plant Pathology
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
everhart@unl.edu

Annick Lenglet (current collaborator)

Epidemiology Adviser Médecins Sans Frontières (Doctors Without Borders) Amsterdam, Netherlands Annick.Lenglet@amsterdam.msf.org

Thibaut Jombart (line manager)

Assistant Professor
Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology
Imperial College London
thibautjombart@gmail.com